Guide to the Charles Dickens Collection 1836-1896
Lewis Clark College Special Collections and Archives
The Charles Dickens Collection
1836-1896
Lewis Clark College Special Collections and Archives Lewis Clark College Special Collections and Archives Aubrey R. Watzek Library 0615 SW Palatine Hill Rd. Portland, OR 97219 archives@lclark.edu 503-768-7254
OLPb136DIC
2 cubic feet 3 boxes
Includes serial publications, original parts, proofs, photographs, and articles about the great English novelist, Charles Dickens. Most of the materials were produced during Dickens' life.
Historical Note
Includes serial publications, original parts, proofs, photographs, and articles.
Arranged alphabetically by novel title, and by format and date for materials not associated with a specific novel.
This collection has no restrictions and is open for research.
Assembled by Paul Merchant and donated to Lewis Clark College in 2011.
The collection will be periodically supplemented with similar materials by Charles Dickens.
Other books by Dickens are housed with Special Collections Rare Books.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Dickens, Charles, 1812-1870
Novelists, English -- 19th century
Literature
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.
- The Posthumous Papers of the Pickwick Club, proof cover, 1836 (Box-folder 1.1)
- Nicholas Nickleby, proof cover and 5 illustrations, 1838 (Box-folder 1.2)
- Martin Chuzzlewit, proof cover, Jan. 1843 (Box-folder 1.3)
- Dombey and Son, proof cover, Dec. 1846 (Box-folder 1.4)
- Dombey and Son, no. 4, Mar. 1847 (Box-folder 1.5)
  Chapters 17-19; London: Bradbury and Evans
- David Copperfield, no. 1, May 1849 (Box-folder 1.6)
  Chapters 1-3; London: Bradbury and Evans
- Bleak House, 15 proofs for original plates, 1852 (Box-folder 1.7)
- Bleak House, no. 1, Mar. 1852 (Box-folder 1.8)
  Chapters 1-4; London: Bradbury and Evans
- The New York Journal, vol. 2 part 2, Jun. 1854 (Box-folder 1.9)
  Hard Times, chapters 7-10; New York: P.D. Orius
- Household Words, vol. 9 no. 5, Sep. 1854 (Box-folder 1.10)
  Hard Times, chapters 20-36; New York: T.L. McElrath and Co.
- Little Dorrit, no. 3, Feb. 1856 (Box-folder 1.11)
  Chapters 9-11; London: Bradbury and Evans
- >Harpers's New Monthly Magazine, vol. 8 no. 68, undated (Box-folder 1.12)
  Little Dorrit, chapters 5-18
- A Tale of Two Cities, proof cover, 1859 (Box-folder 1.13)
- Our Mutual Friend, proof cover, May 1864 (Box-folder 1.14)
- Our Mutual Friend, no. 1, May 1864 (Box-folder 1.15)
  Partial copy, chapters 1-4; London: Chapman and Hall
- The Leisure Hour Library, vol. 3 no. 255, Aug. 1889 (Box-folder 1.16)
  Our Mutual Friend, entire novel; New York: F.M. Lupton
- The Mystery of Edwin Drood, no. 1, Apr. 1870 (Box-folder 1.17)
  Chapters 1-5; London: Chapman and Hall
- Household Words, vol. 8 no. 176, Aug. 1853 (Box-folder 2.1)
  1 original copy, 1 photocopy
- Household Words, part 91 nos. 393-397, Oct. 1857 (Box-folder 2.2)
  The Lazy Tour of Two Idle Apprentices (not by Dickens)
- Doctor Marigold's Prescriptions, the Extra Christmas Number, Dec. 1865 (Box-folder 2.3)
- Mugby Junction, the Extra Christmas Number, Dec. 1866 (Box-folder 2.4)
  Contains 8 stories, 4 by Charles Dickens: "Barbox Brothers"; "Barbox Brothers and Co."; "Main Line: the Boy at Mugby"; "No. 1 Branch Line: The Signalman"
- Advertisements, undated (Box-folder 2.5)
  "The Lazy Tour of Two Idle Apprentices"; "Hard Times"; "New Work of Fiction"
- Charles Dickens, portrait, 1839 (Box-folder 2.6)
- Charles Dickens, portrait photograph, c. 1868 (Box-folder 2.7)
- Emlyn Williams as Dickens, c. 1958 (Box-folder 2.8)
  playbill
- book jacket for The Disappearance of Edwin Drood, by Peter Rowland, cover, 1991 (Box-folder 2.9)
- book jacket for Dickens, Drood, and the Detectives, by Ray Dubberke, cover, 1992 (Box-folder 2.10)
- The Illustrated London News, Jul. 1858 (Box-folder 3.1)
  Illustration and brief description of Dickens reading
- Harper's Weekly, a Journal of Civilization, vol. 4 no. 204, Nov. 1860 (Box-folder 3.2)
  Great Expectations, chapters 1-3
- Harper's Weekly, Feb. 1869 (Box-folder 3.3)
  Article titled "Mr. Charles Dickens's New Reading"
- Every Saturday, an Illustrated Journal of Choice Reading, vol. 1 no. 15, Apr. 1870 (Box-folder 3.4)
  Article on Dickens, illustrations, and chapters 1-2 of T he Mystery of Edwin Drood
- The Graphic, Dec. 1871 (Box-folder 3.5)
  Portrait of Wilkie Collins
- Sheet Music for Dombey and Son, 1896 (Box-folder 3.6)
  "What Are the Wild Waves Saying?", a duet between Paul and Florence; music by Stephen Glover; Boston: F. Trifet